Guide to the Mason Crum Papers, 1885 - 1974
University Archives Duke University
Mason Crum papers 1885 - 1974
Crum, Mason, b. 1887.
6.0 Linear Feet 7,000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
Mason Crum (1887-1980) served as a Professor in the Dept. of Religion at Duke University from 1930 to 1957. He studied race relations and Christianity, as well as social history of the Gullah community of the South Carolina Sea Islands. The papers contain correspondence, printed material, manuscripts of books and articles, clippings, photographs and glass slides, and and a sound recording. Major subjects include religious aspects of race relations and segregation, African American religion and churches, Gullah dialect and culture, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and the Lake Junaluska retreat.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Mason Crum Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973-1977.
Biographical Note
Educator, author, Methodist minister; born Frederick Mason Crum; A.B. Wofford College, 1909; Ph.D., University of South Carolina, 1925; LI.D, 1950. Professor of Biblical Literature, Duke University, 1930-1957. Author, Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands (1940); The Negro in the Methodist Church (1950). Married (1914) Katherine Howell of Waterboro, S.C.; six children.
Mason Crum was born in Rowesville, S.C., the son of William C. and Nonie (Neeley) Crum. His father was a merchant, farmer, and landowner in Orangeburg County. Crum received his undergraduate education at Wofford College, Spartanburg, graduating in 1909. He then attended the School of Religion at Vanderbilt in 1910, and was principal of a school in Fort Mill, S.C. for a year. In 1911, desiring to work for a Ph.D. in order to teach at the college level, he entered Harvard for courses in psychology and philosophy. After a year's study, he returned to South Carolina and began what his autobiography calls a kind of detour in life. During the few next years, he worked as an agent for the Department of Agriculture, sold cars, and became interested in the ministry. He was ordained in the Methodist Church in 1919 and received a pastorate in Summerville, S.C. in 1920. Still desiring to teach, he was appointed Professor of Religious Education at Columbia College. From 1920 to 1930 he taught courses in Biblical literature, psychology, ethics, and education, and completed the Ph.D. program in education at the University of South Carolina, receiving the degree in 1925; his dissertation was on the Project Principle in Religious Education. He was a member and officer of the Chi Phi fraternity.
He began teaching Biblical Literature part-time at Duke University in 1930, and was appointed to the faculty two years later. While at Duke, Crum worked extensively on the question of race relations and Christianity and began studying the social history of the South Carolina Sea Islands, and especially the Gullah communities on Edisto and St. Helena. He took part in cooperative efforts in bettering race relations through education, and was active in a number of organizations. He began teaching a course in Black History, The Negro in the Religious Life of America, in 1954; the course was described as an examination of Christian churches' attempts to apply the Christian ethic to race relations, although Crum intended it as a course about Black life and culture. Crum retired from Duke in 1957, and, after moving to Florida, he volunteered his services as a pastoral counselor to a clinic associated with the Presbyterian Church of Hollywood, Florida. He and his wife returned to North Carolina sometime after 1963, and took up residence at Lake Junaluska, the Methodist Church's retreat in western North Carolina, where Crum died in September, 1980.
Collection Overview
The Mason Crum papers include correspondence, printed material, hand written and typewritten manuscripts of books and articles, clippings, photographs and glass slides, and an audio tape, with the bulk dates being 1931-1959. Crum acquired the materials over the course of his career as a professor of Biblical literature who had interests in Black history, psychology, race relations, and recent Methodist church history. His major area of research was the Gullah communities of Edisto and St. Helena, two of the South Carolina Sea Islands, with the bulk of work here dating from the 1930s; the result of the research was Gullah, published by Duke University Press in 1940. Other areas of interest were moral education, pastoral counseling, and religious pageantry. His concern with Christianity and race relations is shown by his participation in cooperative efforts, and in the teaching of one of the first Black studies courses in the South (1954).
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
African American churches
African Americans -- South Carolina -- Sea Islands
African Americans -- Study and teaching
Crum, Mason, b. 1887
Duke University. Dept. of Religion
Duke University -- Faculty
Edisto Island (S.C.)
Gullahs
Islands -- South Carolina
Methodist Episcopal Church, South
Race relations -- Religious aspects
Religion -- Study and teaching
Sea Islands
Sea Islands Creole dialect
Segregation -- Southern States
St. Helena Island (S.C.)
Clippings
Lantern slides
Photographs
Sound recording
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1900-1974, undated
  Consists of personal and family letters; correspondence from Crum's days as a salesman, and correspondence relating to his activities as an educator and Methodist layman. Among the last is material relating to boys' camps, Methodist Church activities, the Y.M.C.A., letters to publishers, Lake Junaluska Summer School, and Crum's other interests and activities.
  Arranged chronologically, with a sub-series, Subject Correspondence, 1926-1971, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - 1900-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1931-March 1936 (Folder 2)
  - April 1936-1937 (Folder 3)
  - 1938 (Folder 4)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1941 (Folder 6)
  - 1942-1943 (Folder 7)
  - 1944-1945 (Folder 8)
  - 1946-1947 (Folder 9)
  - 1948-October 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - November 1949-1950 (Folder 11)
  - 1951-February 1952 (Folder 12)
  - March 1952-December 1952 (Folder 13)
  - 1953-April 1954 (Folder 14)
  - May 1954-October 1959 (Folder 15)
  - 1960-1967 (Folder 16)
  - 1970-1974 (Folder 17)
  - Undated (Folder 18)
  - Subject Correspondence
    The sub-series, Subject Correspondence, consists of one box with material on: Camp Junaluska for Boys, 1926-1930; Chi Phi fraternity, 1948-1958; correspondence and reviews concerning the publication of Gullah; Lake Junaluska properties, 1949-1958; North Carolina College Teachers of Religion, 1938-1949; correspondence and reactions to his article, A Southerner Looks at Segregation (1954), which was published in The Christian Advocate, November 11, 1954; correspondence concerning cooperative efforts in race relations, 1936-1954. This last contains material from state, college and university, and denominational agencies concerned with bettering race relations. Among the organizations represented are the Division of Cooperation in Education and Race Relations of the North Carolina Dept. of Public Instruction, the University of North Carolina, the Dept. of Race Relations of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, and Duke University. Committee work, conferences, and other activities are represented in the file.
    - Camp Junaluska for Boys, 1926-1930 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Chi Phi fraternity, 1948-1958 (Folder 20)
    - Gullah publication, 1938-1971 (Folder 21)
    - Lake Junaluska, 1949-1958 (Folder 22)
    - North Carolina College Teachers of Religion, 1938-1949 (Folder 23)
    - Race relations, 1936-1954 (Folder 24)
    - A Southerner Looks at Segregation article, 1954-1955 (Folder 25)
- Subject files, 1885-1957, undated
  Printed materials, research notes, a diary and cashbook, and other materials. Personal records include Crum's vitae and genealogy, a diary he kept while at Harvard, and a cashbook (1885-1895) from his father's store in Orangeburg County. Academic materials consist of class rolls, 1930- 1957, course materials, including test materials and clippings concerning his course on Black History, and several student papers. Also in the subject files are records and programs for the Lake Junaluska Assembly, research notes on various topics, including race relations and the Gullah communities, and a bibliography on Black History.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bibliography of the Negro, 1860-1927 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Family genealogical and Mason Crum biographical information (Folder 27)
  - Cashbook, 1885-1895 (Folder 28)
  - Cherokee history (Folder 29)
  - Clippings and reprints, 1951-1954 (Folder 30)
  - Personal clippings, 1935-1957 (Folder 31)
  - Columbia College (Folder 32)
  - Courses
    - Educational Psychology, 1929 (Folder 33)
    - Religion 185, "Negro Americans," 1954-1956 (Folder 34)
    - Religion 169-170, 1932-1933 (Folder 35)
    - Test material, 1957 (Folder 36)
  - Diary from year at Harvard University, 1912 (Folder 37)
  - Lake Junaluska
    - Assembly Programs, 1913-1929 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Assembly Programs, 1930-1951 (Folder 39)
    - Camps, 1927-1931 (Folder 40)
    - Conferences, 1917-1953 (Folder 41)
  - Land management, Orangeville County, S.C., 1928-1948 (Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1921-1960 (Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous published material (Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1894-1930 (Folder 45)
  - Pastor's School, 1926-1934 (Folder 46)
  - Personal and worship notes, reflection on call to ministry (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Printed material (Folder 48)
  - Recommendations [written by others about Mason Crum], 1909-1913 (Folder 49)
  - Race relations (Folder 50)
  - Religio-Psychiatric Clinic, 1957-1963 (Folder 51)
  - Religious education, 1929-1949 (Folder 52)
  - Study of Religion in the Colleges of N.C., ca. 1937 (Folder 53)
  - Sermon notes, 1915-1920 (Folder 54)
  - University of South Carolina, 1950-1951 (Folder 55)
  - Teaching (Folder 56)
- Writings, 1911-1967, undated
  Hand- and typewritten manuscripts, notebooks, bound volumes, together with research notes, for published and unpublished books and articles. Not included are the Guide to Religious Pageantry (published in 1923) and The Project Method in Religion (Ph.D. thesis, University of South Carolina, 1924). Works represented are: 1) Autobiography, tentatively titled The Young Bee Makes the Honeycomb, [1959-1960]. 2) A Boy's Life of Albert Schweitzer, undated 3) Character Building, various dates 4) Cherokee Legends of the Great Smokey Mountains, [1954-1962] 5) Child Development, writings on, various dates 6) Childhood and Character, [1929] 7) College term papers, Harvard, [1911-1912]. 8) Counseling College Students, [1930-1967]. 9) Doorways of Duke, [1950], on Duke architecture. 10) Duke University and the Things of the Spirit, undated 11) Family counseling, writings on, various dates. 12) Fiction, unpublished short stories, various dates. 13) Gullah. Duke University Press, 1940. Bound typescript and personal copy. 14) History of the Southern Christian Advocate, undated The Advocate is a South Carolina Methodist publication. 15) Life Among the Gullah Negroes, undated 16) Life and Times of Washington Duke, undated 17) A Little Girl Named Maggie, [1953, how Maggie Valley, N.C. got its name.] 18) Miscellaneous articles 19) The Negro in the Methodist Church. The Board of Missions and the Church Extension, The Methodist Church, 1951. Bound copy inscribed to Dr. and Mrs. Gross. 20) A Negro Story Nobody Knows: When Negro Methodists sat in Southern Churches (tentative title), undated [on the pre-Civil War period] 21) Writings on Religion 22) A Southerner Looks at Segregation, 1955 23) Speaking of Boys, undated (Chapter 3) 24) The Story of Lake Junaluska, 1950, and Chief Junaluska. 25) Where Your Hillbilly Music Comes From, undated
  - Autobiography
    - Books 1-2, First draft, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Books 3-4, First draft, 1959-1960 (Folder 58)
    - The Young Bee Makes the Honeycomb: The Short and Simple Annals of a College Professor, Chapters 1-11, 1959-1960 (Folder 59)
    - The Young Bee Makes the Honeycomb: The Short and Simple Annals of a College Professor, Chapters 12-20, 1959-1960 (Folder 60)
  - A Boy's Life of Albert Schweitzer (Folder 61)
  - Character Building (Folder 62)
  - Cherokee Indians, 1953-1954 (Folder 63)
  - Cherokee Legends of the Great Smokey Mountains, 1954-1962 (Folder 64)
  - Cherokee Indian legends (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Child development (Folder 66)
  - Childhood and character, 1929 (Folder 67)
  - College term papers, Harvard, 1911-1912 (Folder 68)
  - Counseling college students, 1930-1967 (Folder 69)
  - Doorways of Duke, 1950 (Folder 70)
  - Duke University and things of the spirit (Folder 71)
  - Family counseling, 1919-1953 (Folder 72)
  - Fiction (Folder 73)
  - Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands, 1940
    - Research notes, Gullah life and visit to a Negro Church in Durham (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1940., Signed by the author on the front fly-leaf and on the title page. (Folder 75)
    - Typed manuscript draft, Chapters 1-8, undated (Folder 76)
    - Typed manuscript draft, Chapters 9-14, undated (Folder 77)
    - Dust jacket, Duke University Press, 1940 (Folder 78)
  - History of the Southern Christian Advocate (Box 11, Folder 75)
  - Life Among Gullah Negroes (Folder 76)
  - Life and Times of Washington Duke (Folder 77-80)
  - A Little Girl Named Maggie or Maggie Valley: A True Story from a Great Smoky Mountain Region, 1953 (Folder 81)
  - The Negro in the Methodist Church. New York: Board of Missions and Church Extension, The Methodist Church, 1951., Inscribed by the author on the title page: "To: Dr. Paul Gross and Mrs. Gross from Mason Crum". (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - A Negro History Nobody Knows
    - A Negro History Nobody Knows; When Negro Methodists Sat in Southern Churches, holograph manuscripts, undated (Folder 83)
    - A Negro Story Nobody Knows: The Forgotten Chapter in Southern History, holograph manuscript, 1944 (Folder 84)
    - A Negro Story Nobody Knows, annotated typescript
      - Chapters 1-9 (Folder 85-86)
      - Chapters 10-16 (Folder 87-88)
  - Religion (Box 13, Folder 89)
  - A Southerner Looks at Segregation, 1955 (Folder 90)
  - Speaking of Boys, Chapter 3 (Folder 91)
  - The Story of Lake Junaluska, 1946 (Folder 92-93)
  - Where Your Hillbilly Music Comes From (Folder 94)
- Photographs, 1910, 1930s, undated
  62 10" x 13" black and white prints, many autographed and dated by Mason Crum, mounted on 15" x 20" boards, in two volumes, and numbered; plus one box of snapshots, lantern slides, magazine clippings and small mounted prints. Most of the mounted prints date from 1935-1936, and are landscapes, portraits, buildings and activities in the Gullah communities on the islands of Edisto and St. Helena's; also photographs of charcoal portraits done in the Sea Islands by Winold Reiss of St. Helena, family prints and portraits, and prints of old maps. Most of the remaining photographs are family snapshots, scenes at Lake Junaluska, small prints of the Sea Island photographs, approximately 48 3" x 4" glass lantern slides of Sea Island prints, and scenes at Duke University (including 5" x 7" prints for an article titled 'Doorways of Duke.')
  Unarranged.
  - Photographs (Oversize 14)
    Includes snapshots, lantern slides, clippings, small prints.
  - Mounted photographs 1-30, "Volume 1" (Oversize 15)
  - Mounted photographs 31-60, "Volume 2" (Oversize 16)
- Audio tape, undated
  1 7" reel audio tape, Mason Crum performing "Cotton Field Ballads" said to be illustrative of a chapter in his autobiography on southern songs and ballads.
  Audio tapes are stored with the Sound Recordings collection.
  This recording has been transferred and is available on audio cassette.